Inventory of the John Dixon Papers 1760-1829
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, College of William and Mary
John Dixon Papers, 1760-1829.
Special Collections, College of William and Mary
Mss. 39.1 D64
610 items.
The John Dixon Papers include letters, legal papers, receipts, farm and personal accounts, 1760-1829 of John Dixon, Jr. (1777-1830) of "Airville" Gloucester County, Virginia.
John Dixon
Administrative Information
Restrictions on Access
Collection is open to all researchers.
Acquisition Information
Purchased: 25 items, 01/01/1928.
Gift: 580 items, ca. 1938.
Gift: 1 item, 04/01/1976.
Gift: 4 items, 02/24/1987.
Biographical Information
John Dixon Jr. was born in 1778 and died September 5, 1830. He married Sally (Sarah) Throckmorton, the daughter of Warner and Julia Throckmorton, in 1795. They had three children: Dr. John Dixon(1812- 1835), Isabella S. Burwell, Harriet Peyton. Dixon remarried Mary T. (?). There was one child from this union Mary E. Dixon.
Family History
John Dixon Jr.'s father was John Dixon (d.1788). He married Elizabeth Peyton, daughter of Sir John Peyton of Isleham, Gloucester County, on February 6, 1773. They had four children: John, Lucy, Seigniora, and Betsy.
John Dixon Jr.'s grandfather was the Rev. John Dixon(d.1777). He married Lucy (?). They had five children: John, William, Thomas, Lucy, Elizabeth
John Dixon Jr.'s great grandfather, John Dixon (d.1758) came to Virginia from Bristol, England in the eighteenth century. He married Lucy Reade(1701-1731), daughter of Mr. Thomas Reade of Gloucester. They had three children: Rev. John Dixon, Roger Dixon, and Thomas Dixon. After the death of his first wife, he remarried Ann (?), of King William County. They had four children: Cornelious, Lyonell, Robert, and Susannah Ann. All the male children from this second union died unmarried.
Additional Genealogical Information
Additional family and genealogical information can be found in the first folder of the first box of the John Dixon Papers, Collection number: Mss. 39.1 D64.
Scope and Content Information
The John Dixon Papers include letters, legal papers, farm and personal accounts, 1760-1829 of John Dixon, Jr. (1777-1830) of "Airville" Gloucester County, Virginia.
Letters include those from Charles H. Braxton of "Oak Spring," Burwell Bassett of Williamsburg, Richard Jones, John Nicholson, John Peyton, and James and Samuel Stubbs of Gloucester County. The collection also includes a letter, 22 October 1827, of Burwell Bassett and a letter, 1826, of John Mercer Patton (1796-1858). These papers contain references to the Whiting family of Williamsburg, Virginia.
Papers relate to settlements of estates which John Dixon administered, while early material include copies of the wills of his great-grandfather John Dixon of Bistol, England, his father John Dixon (d. 1788) of Gloucester County, Virginia, and the settlement of the estate of his mother Elizabeth Peyton Dixon.
Additions to the collection include copies of a 1729 land patent, the 1766 will of Roger Dixon and two genealogies of the family.
Organization
These papers have been organized into six series: 1. Family Papers; 2. Letters Written to John Dixon Jr.; 3. Legal Papers of John Dixon Jr.; 4. Other Papers of John Dixon; 5. Business Papers of John Dixon Jr.; 6. Addition.
Index Terms
Family Names:
Dixon family.; Whiting family.
Persons:
Dixon, John, d. 1788.; Dixon, Elizabeth Peyton; Bassett, Burwell, 1764-1841.; Patton, John Mercer, 1796-1858.; Dixon, William M.
Geographical Names:
Gloucester County (Va.)--History--19th century.
Components List
  Series 1: Family Papers
- Family Papers, 1760-1826. (Folder 1)
  - Copy of the will of John Dixon of Bristol, England, 1760., 1 item. Mutilated. (Folder 1)
    John Dixon is the great-grandfather of John Dixon Jr.
  - Estate of John Dixon, Sr., 1778-1816., 25 items. (Folder 1)
    John Dixon is the father of John Dixon Jr. A copy of his will is included among his estate papers.
  - Estate of Elizabeth Dixon, 1797-1826., 19 items. (Folder 1)
    Elizabeth Dixon is the mother of John Dixon Jr.
  - Copy of the will of William M. Dixon, 1775., 1 item. (Folder 1)
  Series 2: Letters Written to John Dixon Jr.
- Letters Written to John Dixon Jr. of Gloucester County, Virginia, 1811-1829, n.d. (Folder 2)
  - John B. Jesse, Middlesex [County], 29 Sept. 1811., 1 item. (Folder 2)
  - John B. Jesse, Middlesex [County], 21 May 1812., 1 item. (Folder 2)
  - John Lind Smith, at Cherleston, S.C., 21 July 1812., 1 item. (Folder 2)
  - Thomas T. T. Tabb, at Seaford, [York County, Virginia], 18 Jan. 1815., 1 item. (Folder 2)
  - Charles H. Braxton, at Pipingtree, [King William County], 1 Feb. 1825., 1 item. (Folder 2)
  - Charles H. Braxton, at Pipingtree, [King William County], 3 March 1825., 1 item. (Folder 2)
  - J. K. Marshall, Fauquier [County], 22 May 1826., 1 item. (Folder 2)
  - John F. Tomkies, at Huntersville, N.C., 20 May 1827., 1 item. (Folder 2)
  - John M. Patton, at Fredericksburg, 31 May 1827., 1 item. (Folder 2)
  - Thomas J. [ ? ], at Baltimore, 1 Aug. 1827., 1 item. Mutilated. (Folder 2)
    This is a printed circular letter.
  - Burwell Bassett, at Williamsburg, 22 Oct. 1827., 1 item. (Folder 2)
  - John R. West, at Yorktown, 2 April 1828., 1 item. (Folder 2)
  - Charles H. Braxton, at Oak Spring, 8 April 1828., 1 item. (Folder 2)
  - C. & G. Clarke, at Richmond, 6 Aug. 1828., 1 item. (Folder 2)
  - R. Patton, Jr., at Fredericksburg, 6 Sept. 1828., 1 item. (Folder 2)
  - Beverley Blair, at Richmond, 2 Oct. 1828., 1 item. (Folder 2)
  - Charles H. Braxton, at Oak Spring, 11 July 1829., 1 item. (Folder 2)
  - Charles H. Braxton, at Oak Spring, n.d., 2 items. (Folder 2)
  - Richard Jones, n.d., 1 item. (Folder 2)
  - John Miller, New Kent [County], n.d., 1 item. (Folder 2)
  - R. Patton, Jr., n.d., 1 item. (Folder 2)
- Letter from Thomas Smith to Mr. Garnett, overseer at Airville, n.d., 1 item. (Folder 2)
  Series 3: Legal Papers
- Legal Papers of John Dixon Jr., 1805-1828. (Folder 3)
  - Assignment made by M. Dixon to John Dixon, 1805., 1 item. (Folder 3)
    Item concerns the transference of M. Dixon's interest in John Gwyn's estate.
  - Power of Attorney given by Benjamin N. Robinson, 1807., 1 item. (Folder 3)
    This item concerns the authorization of Morgan Tomkies to sell slaves.
  - Land papers, 1815., 2 items. (Folder 3)
    Items include a deed given by Warner and Thomas Throcknorton to John Dixon covering a mill dam and a tract of land in Gloucester County, Virginia; and a copy of a court order granting John Dixon permission to erect a mill.
  - Suit in Williamsburg Chancery Court, 1826., 1 item. (Folder 3)
    Kennon and Tomasia Whiting vs. William S. Thornton, administrator of Meaux Thornton et als.
  - Power of attorney given by John Dixon, 1828., 6 items. (Folder 3)
    Items authorize William C. Minor to settle and adjust claims against various persons, and include papers concerning these claims.
  Series 4: Other Papers
- Other Papers of John Dixon Jr., 1807-1823, n.d. (Folder 3)
  - Memorandum of an agreement between John Ellis and John C. Pryor, 1807., 1 item. (Folder 3)
    Item concerns a lease for a tract of land. John Dixon was a witness for this agreement.
  - Agreements of Elihu Hotchkiss with John Dison, 1818., 4 items. (Folder 3)
    Item concern the manufacture and sale of Hotchisses' improved straw cutter.
  - A pre-nuptial agreement between John Grrill and Signiora Banks, 1823., 1 item. (Folder 3)
    Items concern the use and disposal of certain property.
  - Copy of an act of the General Assembly, n.d., 2 items. (Folder 3)
    Item concerns the specifications for staves for hogsheads; and a memorandum concerning other lumber.
  - A printed list of prices of drugs and medicines, n.d., 1 item. (Folder 3)
  Series 5: Papers of John Dixon, Jr.
- Papers of John Dixon, Jr., 1799-1829. (Folder 4-7)
  - Accounts with Newington Academy, 1819 - 1826., 9 items. (Folder 4)
  - Account of the United States with Thomas C. Amory, 1814., 1 item. (Folder 4)
    This item was paid for by John Dixon, quarter master.
  - Invoices, receipts, and tax bills, 1799 - 1829., 230 items. (Folder 4-5)
  - Papers relating to transactions of John Dixon, Jr., with various people, 1802-1826. (Folder 6-7)
    - Transactions with the George Catlett estate and Seigniora Catlett, 1802 - 1827., 80 items. (Folder 6)
    - Transactions with Jones (Richard), 1806 - 1826., 18 items. (Folder 7)
    - Transactions with Peyton (John), 1806 - 1829., 24 items. (Folder 7)
      Items include a copy of his will.
    - Transactions with Stubbs (James), 1803 - 1814., 10 items. (Folder 7)
    - Transactions with Stubbs (Sam), 1819 - 1826., 28 items. (Folder 7)
    - Transactions with Tufts (Ann) and others, 1818 - 1826., 9 items. (Folder 7)
  - Bonds given by John Dixon, Jr., and others to various persons, 1814 - 1824., 13 items. (Folder 7)
  - Accounts of other persons, 1807 -1828., 26 items. (Folder 7)
  Series 6: Addition
- Addition (Othertype Collection number: Mss. 39.1 D64 Sm. Coll. Add 24)
  - Land patent, 1729., Xerox copy and typescript (Folder See above)
    Item is the land patent of John Dixon of Bristol, England.
  - Will, 1757., Typescript (Folder See above)
    Item is the will of John Dixon of Bristol, England.
  - Will, 1766., Typescript (Folder See above)
    Item is the will of Roger Dixon of Fredericksburg, Virginia, second son of John Dixon.
  - Letter, 14 January 1987. (Folder See above)
    Letter from Caroline T. Anderson giving Dixon family genealogy.